1:2 Praise is to God, Lord of the worlds.
1:2. Louvado seja Deus, Senhor do Universo,
1:3 The Gracious, the Compassionate.
1:3. Clemente, o Misericordioso,
1:4 Master of the day of judgment.
1:4. Soberano do Dia do Juízo.
1:5 You alone we serve; you alone we ask for help.
1:5. Só a Ti adoramos e só de Ti imploramos ajuda!
1:6 Guide us to the straight way;
1:6. Guia-nos à senda reta,
1:7 the way of those whom you blessed; not of those who received anger, nor of the strayers.
1:7. À senda dos que agraciaste, não à dos abominados, nem à dos extraviados.
[Ameen]
[Amém]
1. O you prophet, you shall be aware of God, and do not obey the ingrates and the hypocrites. God is Knowledgeable, Wise.
1. Ó Profeta, teme a Deus e não obedeças aos incrédulos, nem aos hipócritas. Fica sabendo que Deus é Sapiente, Prudentíssimo.
2. Follow what is being revealed to you by your Lord. God is fully aware of all that you do.
2. E observa o que te foi inspirado por teu Senhor, porque Deus está inteirado de tudo quanto todos vós fazeis.
3. Put your trust in God. God suffices as an advocate.
3. Confia em Deus, porque basta Ele por Guardião.
4. God did not make any man with two hearts in his body. Nor did He make your wives whom you estrange to be as your mothers. Nor did He make your adopted children to be your sons. Such is what you claim with your mouths, but God speaks the truth, and He guides to the path.
4. Deus não pôs no peito do homem dois corações; tampouco fez com que vossas esposas, as quais repudiais através do zihar, vossas mães, nem fez de vossos filhos adotivos vossos filhos verdadeiros. Estas são vãs palavras das vossas bocas. E Deus diz a verdade, e Ele guia ao caminho certo.
5. Call them by their father's name. That is more just with God. But if you do not know their fathers, then, as your brothers in the system and members of your family. There is no sin upon you if you make a mistake in this respect; but you will be responsible for what your hearts deliberately intend. God is Forgiver, Compassionate.
5. Dai-lhes os sobrenomes dos seus verdadeiros pais; isto é mais equitativo ante Deus. Contudo, se não lhes conheceis os pais. sabei que eles são vossos irmãos, na religião, e vossos tutelados. Porém, se vos equivocardes, não sereis recriminados; (o que conta) são as intenções dos vossos corações; sabei que Deus é Indulgente, Misericordioso.
6. The prophet is closer to those who acknowledge than themselves, and his wives are mothers to them. God's decree to those who acknowledge and the emigrants is that before they help their relatives, they have taken care of their own families first. Such has been decreed in the book.
6. Um profeta tem mais domínio sobre os crentes do que eles mesmos (sobre si), e as esposas dele devem ser (para eles) suas mães. E, segundo o que foi estipulado no Livro de Deus, os consanguíneos têm mais direito entre si do que os crentes e os migrantes. Contudo, fazei o que é justo aos vossos amigos íntimos; isso está escrito no Livro.
7. When We took from the prophets their covenant. From you, and from Noah, and Abraham, and Moses, and Jesus the son of Mary; We took from them a strong covenant.
7. Recorda-te de quando instituímos o pacto com os profetas: contigo, com Noé, com Abraão, com Moisés, com Jesus, filho de Maria, e obtivemos deles um solene compromisso,
8. So that the truthful may be asked about their truthfulness, and He has prepared for the ingrates a painful retribution.
8. Para que (Deus) pudesse interrogar (por vosso intermédio) os verazes, acerca de sua veracidade, e destinar um doloroso castigo aos incrédulos.
9. O you who acknowledge, remember God's favor upon you when soldiers attacked you and We sent upon them a wind and invisible soldiers. God is Seer of everything you do.
9. Ó crentes, recordai-vos da graça de Deus para convosco! Quando um exército se abateu sobre vós, desencadeamos sobre ele um furacão e um exército invisível (de anjos), pois Deus bem via tudo quanto fazíeis.
10. For they came from above you, and from beneath you; and your eyes were terrified, and the hearts reached to the throat, and you harbored doubts about God.
10. (Foi) quando os inimigos vos atacaram de cima e de baixo, e os (vossos) olhos se assombraram, e os (vossos) corações como que (vos) subiam à garganta; nessa altura ainda estáveis a desconfiar de Deus, sob vários aspectos.
11. That is when those who acknowledge were truly tested; they were severely shaken up.
11. Então os crentes foram testados; e foram sacudidos violentamente.
12. The hypocrites and those who have a sickness in their hearts said, "God and His messenger promised us nothing but illusions!"
12. (Foi também) quando os hipócritas e os que abrigavam a enfermidade em seus corações disseram: Deus e Seu Mensageiro não nos prometeram senão ilusões!
13. A group of them said, "O people of Yathrib, you cannot make a stand; therefore, retreat." A small party of them sought permission from the prophet, saying: "Our homes are exposed," while they were not exposed. They just wanted to flee.
13. (Foi ainda) quando um grupo deles (dos crentes) disse: Ó povo de Yáthrib, retornai à vossa cidade, porque não podereis aguentar (o ataque)! E um grupo deles pediu licença (ao Profeta) para retirar- se, dizendo: Certamente nossas casas estão indefesas – quando realmente não estavam indefesas, mas eles pretendiam fugir.
14. If the enemy had entered at them from all sides, and then they were asked to betray, they would do so with very little hesitation.
14. Porém, se (Madina) houvesse sido invadida pelos seus flancos, e se eles houvessem sido incitados à sublevação, a teriam aceito, e poucos teriam hesitado fazê-lo.
15. Indeed they had pledged to God before this that they would not turn around and flee. Making a pledge to God brings great responsibility.
15. Tinham prometido a Deus que não fugiriam (do inimigo). Terão que responder pela promessa feita a Deus!
16. Say, "It will not benefit you to flee away from death or from being killed, for you will only have the enjoyment for a short while."
16. Dize-lhes: A fuga de nada vos servirá, porque, se escapardes à morte ou à matança, não desfrutareis da vida, senão transitoriamente.
17. Say, "Who can protect you from God if He intends to harm you, or He intends any blessing for you?" They will never find besides God any ally or victor.
17. Dize-lhes (mais): Quem poderia resguardar-vos de Deus, se Ele quisesse infligir-vos um mal? Ou se quisesse compadecer-Se de vós? Porém, não encontrarão, para si, além de Deus, protetor, nem socorredor algum.
18. God already knows which of you are the hinderers, and those who say to their brothers: "Come and stay with us." Rarely do they mobilize for battle.
18. Deus conhece aqueles, dentre vós, que impedem os demais de seguirem o Profeta, e dizem a seus irmãos: Ficai conosco!, e não vão à luta, a não ser para permanecerem por pouco tempo.
19. They are miserable towards you. Then, when fear comes, you see their eyes rolling, as if death had already come to them. But once the fear is gone, they lash out at you with sharp tongues. They are miserable towards doing any good. These have not acknowledged, so God nullifies their works. This is easy for God to do.
19. São cobiçosos quanto a vós. Quando o medo se apodera deles, observa (ó Mohammad), que te olham com os olhos injetados, como quem se encontra num transe de morte; porém, quando se lhes desvanece o temor, atacam-te com suas línguas ferinas, cobiçosos quanto ao feitio do bem. Estes não crêem; assim, pois, Deus tornará suas obras sem efeito, porque isso é fácil a Deus.
20. They thought that the opponents had not yet mobilized. If the opponents do appear, they wish that they were out in the desert, seeking out news for you. Even if they were among you, they would not have fought except very little.
20. Imaginavam que os partidos não se houvessem retirado; porém, se os partidos tivessem voltado (a atacar), teriam anelado viver no deserto com os beduínos, para se informarem das vossas ações; e se tivessem estado convosco, não teriam combatido, senão aparentemente.
21. Indeed, in the messenger of God a good example has been set for he who seeks God and the Last day and thinks constantly about God.
21. Realmente, tendes no Mensageiro de Deus um excelente exemplo para aqueles que têm esperança em Deus e no Dia do Juízo Final, e invocam Deus frequentemente.
22. When those who acknowledge saw the opponents, they said, "This is what God and His messenger have promised us, and God and His messenger are truthful." This only increased their acknowledgement and their peacefully surrender.*
22. E quando os crentes avistaram as partidos, disseram: Eis o que nos haviam prometido Deus e o Seu Mensageiro; e tanto Deus como o Seu Mensageiro disseram a verdade! E isso não fez mais do que lhes aumentar a fé e a resignação.
23. From among those who acknowledge are men who fulfilled their pledge to God. Thus, some of them died, while some are still waiting; but they never altered in the least.
23. Entre os crentes, há homens que cumpriram o que haviam prometido a Deus; há-os que já morreram, e outros que esperam, sem violarem a sua promessa, no mínimo que seja.
24. That God may recompense the truthful for their truthfulness, and punish the hypocrites if He so wills, or accepts their repentance. God is Forgiver, Compassionate.
24. Deus recompensa os verazes, por sua veracidade, e castiga os hipócritas como Lhe apraz; ou então os absolve, porque Deus é Indulgente, Misericordiosíssimo.
25. God drove back those who rejected with their rage, they left empty handed. God thus spared those who acknowledge any fighting. God is Powerful, Noble.
25. Deus rechaçou os incrédulos que, apesar da sua fúria, não tiraram vantagem alguma; basta Deus aos crentes, no combate, porque Deus é Potente, Poderoso!
26. He also brought down those who helped support them among the people of the book from their secure positions, and He threw fear into their hearts. Some of them you killed, and some you took captive.
26. E (Deus) desalojou de suas fortalezas os adeptos do Livro, que o (inimigo) apoiaram, e infundiu o terror em seus corações. (Assim que) matastes uma parte e capturastes outra.
27. He inherited you their land, their homes, their money, and lands you had never stepped on. God is able to do all things.
27. E (depois disso) vos fez herdeiros da sua cidade, das suas casas, dos seus bens e das terras que nunca havíeis pisado (antes); sabei que Deus é Onipotente.
28. O prophet, say to your wives: "If you are seeking this worldly life and its vanities, then come, I will make a provision for you and release you in an amicable manner."
28. Ó Profeta, dize a tuas esposas: Se ambicionardes a vida terrena e as suas ostentações, vinde! Prover-vos-ei e dar-vos-ei a liberdade, da melhor forma possível.
29. "But if you are seeking God and His messenger, and the abode of the Hereafter, then God has prepared for the righteous among you a great reward."
29. Outrossim, se preferirdes a Deus, ao Seu Mensageiro e à morada eterna, certamente Deus destinará, para as benfeitoras, dentre vós, uma magnífica recompensa.
30. O wives of the prophet, if any of you commits evident lewdness, then the retribution will be doubled for her. This is easy for God to do.
30. Ó esposas do Profeta, se alguma de vós for culpada de uma má conduta evidente, ser-lhe-á duplicado o castigo, porque isso é fácil a Deus.
31. Any whosoever of you is obedient to God and His messenger, and does good works, We will grant her double the recompense, and We have prepared for her a generous provision.
31. Por outra, àquela que se consagrar a Deus e ao Seu Mensageiro, e praticar o bem, duplicaremos a recompensa e lhe destinaremos um generoso sustento.
32. O wives of the prophet, you are not like any other women. If you are righteous, then do not speak too softly, lest those with disease in their hearts will move with desire; you shall speak in an honorable manner.
32. Ó esposas do Profeta, vós não sois como as outras mulheres; se sois tementes, não sejais insinuantes na conversação, para evitardes a cobiça daquele que possui enfermidade no coração, e falai o que é justo.
33. You shall settle down in your homes, and do not be about like the olden days of ignorance. You shall hold the contact prayer, and contribute towards betterment, and obey God and His messenger. God wishes to remove any affliction from you, O people of the sanctuary, and to purify you completely.
33. E permanecei tranquilas em vossos lares, e não façais exibições, como as da época da idolatria; observai a oração, pagai o zakat, obedecei a Deus e ao seu Mensageiro, porque Deus só deseja afastar de vós a abominação, ó membros da Casa,(1665) bem como purificar-vos integralmente.
34. Mention all that is being recited in your homes of God's signs and the wisdom. God is Sublime, Ever-aware.
34. E lembrai-vos do que é recitado em vosso lar, dos versículos de Deus e da sabedoria, porque Deus é Onisciente, Sutilíssimo.
35. Surely, the peacefully surrendering men, and the peacefully surrendering women, the acknowledging men, and the acknowledging women, the obedient men, and the obedient women, the truthful men, and the truthful women, the patient men, and the patient women, the humble men, and the humble women, the charitable men, and the charitable women, the fasting men, and the fasting women, the men who guard their private parts, and the women who similarly guard, and the men who commemorate God frequently, and the commemorating women; God has prepared for them a forgiveness and a great recompense.
35. Quanto aos muçulmanos e às muçulmanas, aos crentes e às crentes, aos consagrados e às consagradas, aos verazes e às verazes, aos perseverantes e às perseverantes, aos humildes e às humildes, aos caritativos e às caritativas, aos jejuadores e às jejuadoras, aos recatados e às recatadas, aos que se recordam muito de Deus e às que se recordam d'Ele, saibam que Deus lhes tem destinado a indulgência e uma magnífica recompensa.
36. It is not for an acknowledging man or acknowledging woman, if God and His messenger issue any command, that they have any choice in their decision. Anyone who disobeys God and His messenger, he has gone far astray.
36. Não é dado ao crente, nem à crente, agir conforme seu arbítrio, quando é Deus e Seu Mensageiro que decidem o assunto. Sabei que quem desobedecer a Deus e ao Seu Mensageiro desviar-se-á evidentemente.
37. You said to the one who was blessed by God, and blessed by you: "Keep your wife and revere God," and you hid inside yourself what God wished to proclaim. You feared the people, while it was God you were supposed to fear. So when Zayd ended his relationship with his wife, We had you marry her, to establish that there is no wrongdoing for those who acknowledge marrying the wives of their adopted sons if their relationship is ended. God's command is always done.
37. Recorda-te de quando disseste àquele a quem Deus agraciou, e tu favoreceste: Permanece com tua esposa e teme a Deus!, ocultando em teu coração o que Deus ia revelar; temias, acaso, mais as pessoas, sabendo que Deus é mais digno de que O temas? Porém, quando Zaid resolveu dissolver o seu casamento, com a necessária (formalidade), permitimos que tu a desposasses, a fim de que os crentes não tivessem inconvenientes em contrair matrimônio com as esposas de seus filhos adotivos, sempre que estes decidissem separar-se, com a necessária (formalidade); e fica sabendo que o mandamento de Deus deve ser cumprido.
38. There is no blame on the prophet in doing anything that God has decreed upon him. Such was God's sunna with the people of old. God's command is a determined duty
38. Não será recriminado o Profeta por cumprir o que Deus lhe prescreveu, porque foi uma prática (aprovada por) Deus, entre os que o precederam. Os desígnios de Deus são de ordem irrevogável.
39. Those who deliver God's messages, and revere Him, and they do not revere anyone but God. God suffices as a Reckoner.
39. (É a lei) daqueles que transmitem as Mensagens de Deus e O temem, e a ninguém temem, senão a Deus, e basta Deus para que Lhe rendam contas.
40. Muhammed was not the father of any man among you, but he was the messenger of God and the seal of the prophets. God is fully aware of all things.
40. Em verdade, Mohammad não é o pai de nenhum de vossos homens, mas sim o Mensageiro de Deus e o derradeiro dos profetas; sabei que Deus é Onisciente.
41. O you who acknowledge, you shall remember God frequently.
41. Ó crentes, mencionai frequentemente Deus.
42. Glorify Him morning and evening.
42. E glorificai-O, de manhã e à tarde.
43. He is the One who supports you, along with His controllers, to lead you out of darkness into the light. He is ever Compassionate towards those who acknowledge.
43. Ele é Quem vos abençoa, assim como (fazem) os Seus anjos, para tirar-vos das trevas e levar-vos para a luz; sabei que Ele é Misericordioso para com os crentes.
44. Their greeting the day they meet Him is: "Peace" and He has prepared for them a generous recompense.
44. A saudação deles, no dia em que comparecerem ante Ele, será: Paz! E está-lhes destinada uma generosa recompensa.
45. O prophet, We have sent you as a witness, and a bearer of good news, and a warner.
45. Ó Profeta, em verdade, enviamos-te como testemunha, alvissareiro e admoestador!
46. Inviting to God, by His leave, and a guiding beacon.
46. E, como convocador (dos humanos) a Deus, com Sua anuência, e como uma lâmpada luminosa.
47. Give good news to those who acknowledge, that they have deserved from God a great blessing.
47. E anuncia aos crentes, que obterão de Deus infinita graça.
48. Do not obey the ingrates and the hypocrites, and ignore their insults, put your trust in God; God suffices as an advocate.
48. E não obedeças aos incrédulos, nem aos hipócritas, e não faças caso de suas injúrias; confia em Deus, porque Deus te basta por Guardião.
49. O you who acknowledge, if you married the acknowledging women and then divorced them before having intercourse with them, then there is no interim required of them. You shall compensate them, and let them go in an amicable manner.
49. Ó crentes, se vos casardes com as crentes e as repudiardes, antes de haverde-las tocado, não lhes exijais o cumprimento do término estabelecido; dai-lhes um presente, e libertai-as decorosamente.
50. O prophet, We have made lawful for you the wives to whom you have already given their dowry, and the one who is committed to you by oath, as granted to you by God, and the daughters of your father's brothers, and the daughters of your father's sisters, and the daughters of your mother's brothers, and the daughters of your mother's sisters, of whom they have emigrated with you. Also, the acknowledging woman who had decreed herself to the prophet, the prophet may marry her if he wishes, as a privilege given only to you and not to those who acknowledge. We have already decreed their rights in regard to their spouses and those who are still dependants. This is to spare you any hardship. God is Forgiver, Compassionate.
50. Ó Profeta, em verdade, tornamos lícitas, para ti as esposas que tenhas dotado, assim como as que a tua mão direita possui – que Deus tenha feito cair em tuas mãos –, as filhas de teus tios e tuas tias paternas, as filhas de teus tios e tuas tias maternas, que migraram contigo, bem como toda a mulher crente que se dedicar ao Profeta, por gosto, e uma vez que o Profeta queira desposá-la; este é um privilégio exclusivo teu, vedado aos demais crentes. Bem sabemos o que lhes impusemos (aos demais), em relação às suas esposas e às que suas mãos direitas possuem, a fim de que não haja inconveniente algum para ti. E Deus é Indulgente, Misericordioso.
51. You may postpone whom you will of them, and you may receive whom you will. Whomsoever you seek of those whom you have set aside then there is no sin upon you. Such is best that they may be comforted and not grieve, and may all be pleased with what you give them. God knows what is in your hearts. God is Knowledgeable, Compassionate.
51. Podes prescindir (quando da vez) delas, as que desejares e tomar as que te agradarem; e se desejares tomar de novo a qualquer delas que tiveres prescindido (quando da vez dela), não terás culpa alguma. Esse proceder será sensato para que se refresquem seus olhos, não se aflijam e se satisfaçam com o que tiveres concedido a todas, pois Deus sabe o que encerram os vossos corações; e Deus, é Tolerante, Sapientíssimo.
52. No women are lawful to you beyond this, nor that you change them for other wives, even though you may be attracted by their beauty, except those to whom you are committed by oaths. God is watchful over all things.9
52. Além dessas não te será permitido casares com outras, nem trocá- las por outras mulheres, ainda que suas belezas te encantarem, com exceção das que a tua mão direita possua. E Deus é Observador de tudo.
53. O you who acknowledge, do not enter the prophet's homes except if you are invited to a meal, without you forcing such an invitation. But if you are invited, you may enter. When you finish eating, you shall leave, without staying to wait for a hadith. This used to annoy the prophet, and he was shy to tell you. But God does not shy away from the truth. If you ask his wives for something, ask them from behind a barrier. This is purer for your hearts and their hearts. It is not for you to harm God's messenger, nor you should marry his wives after him. This is a gross offence with God.10
53. Ó crentes, não entreis nas casas do Profeta, salvo se tiverdes sido convidados a uma refeição, mas não chegueis muito cedo para aguardardes a sua preparação. Porém, se fordes convidados, entrai; e quando tiverdes sido servidos, retirai-vos sem fazer colóquio familiar, porque isso molestaria o Profeta e este se envergonharia de vós; porém, Deus não Se envergonha da verdade. E se desejardes perguntar algo a elas (suas esposas), fazei-o detrás de cortinas; isso será mais puro para os vossos corações e para os delas. Não vos é dado molestar o Mensageiro de Deus, nem jamais desposar as suas esposas, depois dele, porque isso seria grave ante Deus.
54. If you reveal anything, or hide it, God is fully aware of all things.
54. Quer manifesteis algo, quer o oculteis, sabei que Deus é Conhecedor de todas as coisas.
55. There is no sin upon them before their fathers, or their sons, or their brothers, or the sons of their brothers, or the sons of their sisters, or their offspring yet to come, or their women, or those who are still their dependants. Be aware of God, for God is witness over all things.
55. (As esposas do Profeta) não serão recriminadas (se aparecerem a descoberto) perante seus pais, seus filhos, seus irmãos, seus sobrinhos, perante suas mulheres crentes ou as que suas mãos direitas possuam (servas). E temei a Deus, porque Ele é Testemunha de tudo.
56. God and His controllers support the prophet. O you who acknowledge, you shall support him, and yield completely.
56. Em verdade, Deus e Seus anjos abençoam o Profeta. Ó crentes, abençoai-o e saudai-o reverentemente!
57. Surely those who harm God and His messenger, God will curse them in this life and in the Hereafter; and He has prepared for them a shameful retribution.
57. Em verdade, àqueles que molestam a Deus e ao Seu Mensageiro, Deus os amaldiçoará neste mundo e no outro, e tem-lhes preparado um afrontoso castigo.
58. Those who harm the acknowledging men and the acknowledging women, with no just reason, they have brought upon themselves a slander and a gross sin.
58. E aqueles que molestarem os crentes e as crentes imerecidamente, serão culpados de uma falsa imputação e de um delito flagrante.
59. O prophet, tell your wives, your daughters, and the wives of those who acknowledge that they should lengthen upon themselves their outer garments. That is better so that they would be recognized and not harmed. God is Forgiver, Compassionate.
59. Ó Profeta, dize às tuas esposas, tuas filhas e às mulheres dos crentes que (quando saírem) se cubram com as suas mantas; isso é mais conveniente, para que se distingam das demais e não sejam molestadas; sabei que Deus é Indulgente, Misericordiosíssimo.
60. If the hypocrites, and those with disease in their hearts and those who spread lies in the city do not refrain, then We will let you overpower them, then they will not be able to remain as your neighbors except for a short while.
60. Se os hipócritas e os que abrigam a enfermidade em seus corações, e os intrigantes, em Madina, não se contiverem, ordenar-te-emos combatê-los; então, não ficarão nela, como teus vizinhos, senão por pouco tempo.
61. They are cursed wherever they are found, and they are taken and killed in numbers.
61. Serão malditos: onde quer que se encontrarem, deverão ser aprisionados e cruelmente mortos.
62. This is God's way with those who have passed away before, and you will not find any change in God's way.
62. Tal foi a Lei de Deus, para com aqueles que viveram anteriormente. Nunca acharás mudanças na Lei de Deus!
63. The people ask you regarding the moment. Say, "Its knowledge is with God. For all that you know the moment may be near!"
63. As pessoas te interrogarão sobre a Hora (do Juízo). Dize-lhes: Seu conhecimento somente está com Deus! E o que te fará entender? Talvez a Hora esteja próxima?
64. God has cursed the ingrates, and He has prepared for them hell.
64. Em verdade, Deus amaldiçoou os incrédulos e lhes preparou o Fogo abrasador,
65. Eternally they abide therein. They will find no ally, or victor.
65. Onde permanecerão eternamente; não encontrarão protetor ou socorredor.
66. On the day when their faces will be turned over in the fire, they will say, "Oh, we wish we had obeyed God, and obeyed the messenger"
66. No dia em que os seus rostos estiverem voltados para o fogo, dirão: Oxalá tivéssemos obedecido a Deus e ao Mensageiro!
67. They will say, "Our Lord, we have obeyed our leaders and our learned ones, but they misled us from the path."
67. E dirão (mais): Ó Senhor nosso, em verdade, obedecíamos aos nossos chefes, os quais nos desviaram da (verdadeira) senda.
68. "Our Lord, give them double the retribution, and curse them with a mighty curse."
68. Ó Senhor nosso, redobra o castigo àqueles e amaldiçoa-os reiteradamente!
69. O you who acknowledge, do not be like those who harmed Moses, but then God cleared him of all they said, and he was honorable before God.
69. Ó crentes, não sejais como aqueles que injuriaram Moisés, e sabei que Deus o isentou do que diziam, porque era nobre aos Olhos de Deus.
70. O you who acknowledge, be aware of God and speak only the truth.
70. Ó crentes, temei a Deus e dizei palavras apropriadas.
71. He will then direct your works, and forgive your sins. Whosoever obeys God and His messenger has attained a great triumph.
71. Ele emendará as vossas ações e vos absolverá dos vossos pecados; e quem obedecer a Deus e ao Seu Mensageiro terá logrado um magnífico benefício.
72. We have offered the trust to the heavens and the earth, and the mountains, but they refused to bear it, and were fearful of it. But the human being accepted it; he was transgressing, ignorant.
72. Por certo que apresentamos a custódia ao firmamento, à terra e às montanhas, que se negaram e temeram recebê-la; porém, o homem se encarregou disso, mas provou ser injusto e insipiente.
73. So that God may punish the hypocrite men and the hypocrite women, and the men who set up partners and the women who set up partners. God redeems the acknowledging men and the acknowledging women. God is Forgiver, Compassionate.
73. Deus castigará os hipócritas e as hipócritas, os idólatras e as idólatras, e perdoará os crentes e as crentes, porque Deus é Indulgente, Misericordiosíssimo.
[God is the greatest]
[Deus é o maior]